Anna Klezovich

NLP researcher

♀ 109451 Moscow, Perervinskiy boulevard 8, 125

+7 968 514 43 04

□ anna.klezovich@yandex.ru

hse.ru/staff/aklezovich

Conferences

Poster presentation at LabPhon 17, Vancouver (online)

06/072020 - 08/07/2020

Association for Laboratory Phonology

Semi-automatic Extraction of Handshape Inventory in Russian Sign Language

(https://labphon.org/sites/default/files/current_conference/LabPhon_17_List_of_Papers.pdf)

Oral presentation at FEAST 2020, Paris (online)

23/06/2020 - 25/06/2020

FEAST website

Phonemic Handshape Inventory in Russian Sign Language

Presentation at Young Typologists, St. Petersburg, Russia

21/11/2019 - 23/11/2019

Институт лингвистических исследований РАН (Санкт-Петербург)

Poster presentation at 52nd Annual Meeting of the Societas Linguistica Europaea (SLE 2019), Leipzig, Gemany

21/08/2019 - 24/08/2019

Societas Linguistica Europaea

Poster on the Categorical Status of Adjectives in Russian Sign Language

Book of abstracts

International Cognitive Linguistics Conference, Nishinomiya, 06/08/2019 - 11/08/2019 Japan

International Cognitive Linguistics Association

Endresen, Anna; Klezovich, Anna; Lyashevskaya, Olga; Mordashova, Daria; Nordrum, Maria; Rakhilina, Ekaterina; Tyers, Francis M.; Zhukova, Valentina. Building a Construction for Russian: How to identify families of constructions?

Book of abstracts

Oral presentation at Workshop "Iconicity in Language"at the 06/03/2019 - 08/03/2019 41st meeting of the German Linguistic Society (DGfS), Bremen, Germany

German Linguistic Society (DGfS)

Presentation on the quantitative analysis of lexical iconicity in sign languages. Our abstract

Poster presentation at International Summer School "Areal Linguistics and Languages of Russia", Moscow, Russia

10/09/2018 - 14/09/2018

HSE University

Presentation on the syntactic structure of the nominal complex in Russian Sign Language

Oral presentation at Syntax of the World's Languages 8, Paris, 03/09/2018 - 05/09/2018

France

Institut National des Langues et Civilisations Orientales

Presentation on the word order in the nominal domain in Russian Sign Language. Book of abstracts.

Poster presentation at "Constructional semantics: Cognitive, 24/08/2018 - 25/08/2018 functional and typological approaches" Conference, Helsinki, Finland

The Linguistic Association of Finland, Research project "Temporal movement and manner of motion", the University of Helsinki and the Emil Öhmann Foundation

Presentation on constructional change in Russian expressions with quantitative semantics. Book of abstracts.

Poster presentation at the 11th edition of the Language Resources and Evaluation Conference, Miyazaki, Japan

07/05/2018 - 12/05/2018

Japanese Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology (MEXT)

Book of abstracts and full paper on a database of iconicity patterns in sign languages and its creation and use.

Poster presentation at Summer School of Typology and Lexicon (TyLex) 2017, Young Linguists' International Conference, Moscow, Russia

01/09/2017 - 08/09/2017

HSE University

Presentation on typology of iconicity patterns in sign languages. Book of abstracts.

Poster presentation at Symposium Russian Constructicon 2017, Moscow, Russia

03/2017

HSE University

Presentation on "Phrasal Diachronicon" Database

Oral presentation at ConCorT (Corpus Technologies. Digital Humanities and 10/2016 Modern Knowledge Conference), Nizhny Novgorod, Russia

National Research University Higher School of Economics, Nizhny Novgorod

A presentation on quantitative expressions in Russian, with a particular look on the "po polnoy programme" expression.

Teaching experience

Teacher, programming in python (for 1st and 2nd year bachelor students)

09/2019 - 06/2020

HSE University, School of Linguistics

Developing seminars and assignments, teaching seminars

Course for the 1st year students

Course for the 2nd year students

Education

Bachelor in Fundamental and Applied Linguistics

2015 - 2019

HSE University, Russian Federation

GPA: 9.06 / 10.00

Exchange Student at the University of Bern for the spring semester 01/2018 - 06/2018 **2018**

University of Bern

I accomplished one English-taught (Ethnolinguistics and History of Asia) and 5 German-taught courses (Argumentmarkierung in den Sprachen der Welt, Deutsch Grammatik B2, Deutsch Integrationskurs B2/C1, Kritik des Wortbegriffs, Typologie).

Research Experience

Researcher in the Research and Study Group 'Modality Effects in the Syntax of Russian Sign Language'

01/2018 - now

HSE University

- * Syntactic structure of the nominal domain in Russian Sign Language with the focus on the word order of ominal modifiers. (Experienced in the linguistic fieldwork)
- * Automatic extraction of phonemic handshapes in Russian Sign Language. (Experienced in the basic computer vision methods, such as OpenCV, OpenPose etc.)

Intern-researcher 04/2019 - 12/2019

Linguistic Convergence Laboratory

Student-researcher

09/2017 - 12/2017

Linguistic Laboratory of Corpus Technologies, HSE University

Building a database of the Russian quantitative expressions with their analysis and a website "Phrasal Diachronicon". The novelty of this research was in taking into account a diachronic aspect of the constructions under the framework of Construction Grammar theory.

Programming Skills

- **Python** (machine learning, data analysis, data visualization, statistics, web-applications, databases, neural networks, information retrieval, web scrapping, APIs, natural language processing, theory of algorithms, computer vision) *Advanced knowledge*
- **R** (data visualization, data analysis, Bayesian statistics, mixed-effects models, MCA/PCA, kappas for agreement reliability) *Advanced knowledge*
- **SQL** Intermediate knowledge
- Matlab (neural networks) Intermediate knowledge

Languages

- Russian Native speaker
- English C1 (overall 8, Academic IELTS Certificate from 15/12/2018)
- German B2 level, 4 years of experience
- Russian Sign Language Beginner level (1 out of 3), for research interests

Extracurricular activities

- Since 2015 I actively participate in organizing school competitions in linguistics and Russian language for schoolchildren. I have also volunteered as an examiner and an author of linguistic puzzles at several of them (interview 06/10/2016).
- Volunteer at educational event "Total Dictation" (16-20/04/2016). This event aims at spreading knowledge about Russian grammar and punctuation and raising popularity of writing correctly.

Other Achievements

- Prize winner of Students' Scientific-Research Works Competition at the National Research University Higher School of Economics 2017 (list of winners)
- Recipient of an academic excellence scholarship at the National Research University Higher School of Economics (spring semester 2018)

